Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is בבא קמא צ"ה,
Bava Kamma Tzadi-Heh, בבא קמא Bava Kamma 95. We pick up two
lines from the bottom on צ"ד עמוד ב', Tzadi-Dalet Amud-Bet, three words
from the end of the line והשתא דאמר רב נחמן. V'hashta d'amar
Rav Nachman. And we are dealing with the תקנה takkanah of רבי.
Rebbi. רבי Rebbi made a תקנה takkanah that when a גזלן gazlan
or somebody who lends money with ריבית ribbis comes to do תשובה,
teshuvah, we are not supposed—and to return the money that they stole
or their ill-gotten gains—we are supposed to refuse it in order to
make it easier for them to do תשובה. teshuvah. That itself is
a fascinating idea that somehow we're worried more about their soul and
their repentance than we are about justice, but it is possible to
understand that that is a concern for the betterment of society because
we really don't want them to continue lending with ריבית ribbis and
to continue stealing, and maybe that was sort of the tradeoff that
רבי Rebbi made. Either way, that's the teaching that we are not
supposed to accept it when they come to return. But now we're
going to qualify that. והשתא דאמר רב נחמן בשאין גזילה קיימת, V'hashta
d'amar Rav Nachman b'she'ein gezeilah kayyemes, now that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says
that actually רבי Rebbi is only talking about a case when the
stolen object is no longer around, but if the stolen object is
still around—somebody stole my laptop and they want to do תשובה teshuvah
and he still has my laptop—then that's like a very blatant sense
of injustice and of ownership is very explicit and in that case,
I am supposed to accept it back. Okay? So also maybe the
thinking is that it's harder for asking him to liquidate his funds
and that's an obstacle to תשובה teshuvah more than it is—more than
returning the actual גזילה, gezeilah, the stolen objects themselves; maybe it's less
of an obstacle of תשובה. teshuvah. So one way or another, רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says that רבי's Rebbi's תקנה takkanah does not apply
when the actual stolen object is still around, that then you would
accept it back. והשתא דאמר רב נחמן בשאין גזילה קיימת, V'hashta d'amar
Rav Nachman b'she'ein gezeilah kayyemes, that רבי Rebbi is only talking when
the stolen object is not around, אידי ואידי לאחר תקנה. iidi v'iidi
l'achar takkanah. You can even say that both of these teachings that
we had yesterday—we had a seeming contradiction of ברייתות braitos about whether
you accept the money back or not—so now we have a way
to reconcile them. One way we reconciled them was one was before
רבי's Rebbi's תקנה takkanah you would accept it, and one was after
רבי's Rebbi's תקנה takkanah you would not accept it. But now we
can actually say they both are after רבי's Rebbi's תקנה, takkanah, but
it still matters the circumstances. ולא קשיא, V'lo kashya, top of צ"ה
עמוד א', Tzadi-Heh Amud-Aleph, כאן מגזילה קיימת כאן בשאין גזילה קיימת. kahn
m'gezeilah kayyemes kahn b'she'ein gezeilah kayyemes. There's a difference between whether it's
around or not around. The teaching of רבי Rebbi that
you would not accept the object back is when the original object
was not around, and the teaching of the ברייתא braita that you
would accept the object back was when the object, the money back
or the object back, is when the original object was around. But
now the גמרא Gemara says, "Wait a minute, does that really work
in רבי's Rebbi's תקנה?" takkanah? והא אבנט גזילה קיימת היא. V'ha avneit
gezeilah kayyemes hee. But the whole story about why רבי Rebbi made
a תקנה takkanah is because when somebody wanted to return the money
and do תשובה, teshuvah, his wife said, "You know, if you start
doing תשובה teshuvah and returning everything you stole, you won't even be
able to keep your own אבנט, avneit, your own belt, you'll have
to go naked, you'll have to return everything." So it sounds like
the belt was the stolen object that was still around and רבי's
Rebbi's תקנה takkanah is it does not have to be returned. So
the גמרא Gemara says, "No. מאי אבנט דמי אבנט." Mai avneit d'mei
avneit. It doesn't literally mean that the belt itself was stolen. It
means the cost of the belt, meaning we'll have to sell all
of our property and liquidate all of our property in order to
get the money to pay back everybody. But it does not mean
that we're dealing that the actual stolen item is still around. And
if the stolen item is still around, then
רבי Rebbi might—the argument is that in that case רבי Rebbi said
you would receive—take the item back if he came to return it.
Okay. והרי מריש, V'harei marish, the גמרא Gemara says one minute, we
have another perfect, great, classic example of a תקנת השבים, takkanas hashavim,
a תקנה takkanah that's made to make it easier for people to
do תשובה, teshuvah, and that's a case where the actual stolen object
is still around. The case is מריש, marish, it's like a beam
that somebody built into their roof and there we always say that
because of a תקנה takkanah they don't have to go ahead and
destroy their roof and return the beam. So that's a
case though that the גזילה gezeilah is actually around. והמריש שגזל ובנאו
בבירה, V'hamarish shegazal u'vno b'birah, that there was a תקנה takkanah made
for a stolen beam that was built into a house, into a
castle,
שיטול דמיו, sheyitol damav, that the owner can just take the money
for it but not the object itself, מפני תקנת השבים, mipnei takkanas
hashavim, for the sake of תקנת השבים. takkanas hashavim. So there you
see the object was around and we did not demand that the
object goes back. So the גמרא Gemara says, "No. שאני התם דכיון
דאיכא פסידא דבירה שויוה רבנן כדליתא." Shani hatam d'keivan d'ika psayda d'birah
shavyi rabbanan k'd'leisa. There it's different. There it would actually not just
cause giving back the object itself but destroying the whole house, destroying
the whole roof.
So the normal principle is when the object is around you return
it, but if that would cause tremendous additional loss, not just the
loss of the object, then that would also be covered. by the
תקנת השבים Takkanat Hashavim and therefore you would not have to return
it, which by the way also explains why you're paying for its
value because Rebbi's תקנת השבים Takkanat Hashavim that we've been dealing with
is the גזלן gazlan doesn't pay anybody back, which is pretty shocking,
you know, in order to get him to do תשובה teshuva he
doesn't have to make any compensation. Okay, this מריש marish though, he
is making compensation for the case of the beam, why? Because since
the גזילה gezeila is around he should be returning it even with
Rebbi's תקנה. takkanah. We don't demand it because it would mean destroying
the whole, but because he should be returning it he is going
to pay for its value. Okay. So that's the end of the
discussion of Rebbi's תקנה. takkanah. גזל פרה מעוברת וילדה, Gazal parah meuberet
veyaldah, okay, now we're going on to the next part of the
משנה mishna which speaks about somebody who stole a pregnant cow and
gave birth or a sheep ready to be sheared and sheared it,
and in that case it says that, you know, you return the
object as it is to the owner, you know, the sheared sheep
plus the difference plus you know how much the sheep was worth
when it was stolen because it had all of that wool on
its body, okay, which is not, which is less than the current
state of the sheep plus the shearings, right? That's now you've actually
realized those gains and you've put in the effort and the labor.
Okay, but so you would not have to give back the shearings
and you're קונה koneh the shearings with a שינוי, shinuy, but you
did steal the sheep with the wool on it so you pay
for that difference. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, we taught in a
ברייתא braita that actually is a debate of the תנאים. tannaim. הגוזל
רחל וגזזה, Hagozel rachel vegezezah, somebody stole a sheep and sheared it,
פרה וילדה Parah veyaldah or a cow and it gave birth, משלם
אותה ואת גיזותיה ואת ולדותיה, Meshalem otah ve'et gizoteiha ve'et veladoteiha, you
pay it back together with the shearings and with the new calf,
you know, in the case of the cow, דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei
Rebbi Meir, that's Rebbi Meir says. Rebbi Meir says you actually give
it all back even though it underwent a שינוי. shinuy. רבי יהודה
אומר גזילה חוזרת בעיניה, Rebbi Yehuda omer gezeila chozeret be'eineha,
no, you give it back the way you know you don't give
back the shearings or, you know, the calf, you give back the
stolen object as it is right now, the sheared sheep and the
non-pregnant cow, and as רש״י Rashi says obviously plus the difference of
how much more it was worth when you stole it, okay, which
is the teaching of our משנה. mishna. רבי שמעון אומר רואין אותו
כאילו הוא שומא אצלו בכסף, Rebbi Shimon omer ro'in oto ke'ilu hu
shuma etzlo bechesef, no, Rebbi Shimon says you assess the value at
the moment it was stolen and that's what you pay back. So
that sounds pretty similar to רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. So we're going
to deal with the difference between רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon tomorrow, but today we're just going to focus on
the position of רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. Okay. So, איבעיא להו, Iba'ya
lehu,
so the question was raised, מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר? Mai ta'ama deRebbi
Meir? What's the reason of Rebbi Meir that says you have to
give the original owner back the shearings and the calf? אי משום
דקסבר שינוי במקומו עומד? Ei mishum dekasvar shinuy bimkomo omed?
Does Rebbi Meir hold that שינוי shinuy stands in its place? We
don't recognize שינוי shinuy and therefore the owner is not, the גזלן
gazlan is not קונה koneh it, so it all still belongs to
the owner, so it all goes back to the owner. Okay, that
was a position we saw yesterday. במקומו עומד. Bimkomo omed. או דלמא
O dilma or maybe בעלמא שינוי קונה, be'alma shinuy koneh, really normally
his principle is שינוי shinuy you would be קונה. koneh. Really you
should own, you the גזלן gazlan should own the shearings and the
calf. והכא קנסא הוא דקקניס, Vehacha knasa hu dekakanis, but he's making
a קנס, knas, he's making a fine, a monetary penalty. You stole
from this guy? Even though technically you own the shearings and you
own the calf, we're not going to let you keep it and
we're going to demand that you give it back to the owner.
Okay, למאי נפקא מינה, Lemai nafka mina, the גמרא Gemara says what
practical difference would it mean make if it's a fine or if
it's fundamentally you don't own it? להיכא דכחשא שמכחש, Leheicha dechahasha shemekachash,
if actually if this guy stole it and actually became worth less,
okay, not worth more, and therefore if you say that שינוי shinuy
is קונה, koneh, then in that type of a case we consider
that it got worse in a way that actually the object itself
underwent a שינוי, shinuy, you know, the cow or whatever underwent a
שינוי shinuy and then you would now own the cow and own
the sheep because שינוי shinuy is קונה koneh and you would pay
the difference in terms of from the time that you stole it.
That's if we would say fundamentally שינוי shinuy is קונה koneh and
it was just a קנס. knas. Well here there's no קנס, knas,
here it's actually worth less, so you're stuck with the object and
you pay what it was worth at the time that you stole
it. If however we say שינוי shinuy is not seen as having
taken place, it's not meaningful at all, then you basically would just
give it back to the owner and say here's the object I
stole, okay, and the fact that it's now different and worse would
not be something you would have to pay for. So that would
be the נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Okay, so let's take a look.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, so we're going actually look
at a case where the object became worth less. גזל בהמה והזקינה,
עבדים והזקינו, Gazal behema vehizkina, avadim vehizkinu,
you stole an animal and it became old, and slaves and they
got old, okay, so now they're worth a lot less and that's
some type of a שינוי shinuy and they're worth a lot less.
משלם כשעת הגזלה. Meshalem Kesha'as Gezeila.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kama says you pay like when you stole
it. You were קונה Koneh them with a שינוי Shinoy and therefore
you figure out how much it was when you stole it, and
that's what you pay. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir Omer, Rabbi Meir
says by עבדים, Avadim,
by slaves, you say הרי שלך לפניך. Harei shelcha lefanecha. Why? Because
the principle is that קרקע אינה נגזלת, Karka eina nigzeles, that land
is not stolen, and so no קנייני גזילה Kinyanei gezeila work by
land. And therefore by
slaves—and slaves are often we say הוקשו לקרקעות, Hukshu l'karka'os, there's actually
whole סוגיאס Sugyas whether slaves are like קרקע, Karka, like land, or
like מטלטלין, Metaltelin, like chattel. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying
that slaves are like land and therefore the שינוי Shinoy is not
meaningful. You're not קונה Koneh the slave even though he got old.
So the slave, you return it, it belongs to the owner, and
if it got worse, it got worse under the owner's control and
property. It's not, you don't have to pay for it. But by
the animal, the בהמה, Beheima, that actually you would be קונה Koneh
it and that I agree to the תנא קמא, Tanna Kama, you
pay like the original cost when you stole it. So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is basically agreeing fundamentally that שינוי Shinoy is קונה Koneh
and you pay like when you stole it. He's only saying that
when it comes to the slaves, slaves is an exception and שינוי
Shinoy is not קונה, Koneh, so you give the slave back. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says that seems to answer our question. Let's
take a look. So it says, ואילו בהמה, V'ilu Beheima, the suggestion
by רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is that when it were to come
to the actual animal and not the slave, ואילו בהמה כשעת הגזלה,
V'ilu Beheima Kesha'as Gezeila,
that actually you would be קונה, Koneh, you can't say הרי שלך
לפניך, Harei shelcha lefanecha, here's yours, take it back. No, you are
קונה Koneh it and you would pay like when you stole it.
So you see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds שינוי Shinoy is
קונה. Koneh.
ואי סלקא דעתך סבר רבי מאיר שינוי במקומו עומד, V'issaka Daitach Savar
Rabbi Meir Shinoy Bimkomo Omeid, and if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir were
to hold that
שינוי במקומו עומד, Shinoy Bimkomo Omeid,
I'm sorry, I just lost my place, oh, שינוי במקומו עומד, Shinoy
Bimkomo Omeid, אפילו בהמה נמי, Afilu Beheima Nami, so then you should
be able to say by the בהמה Beheima as well הרי שלך
לפניך, Harei shelcha lefanecha, take it back. But you can't. So he
says, אלא לאו שמע מינה קסבר רבי מאיר שינוי קונה. Ela Lav
Shma Mina Kasavar Rabbi Meir Shinoy Koneh. It must be רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir holds that שינוי Shinoy is קונה Koneh and therefore when
you steal the animal and it gets old, you now own the
animal and you have to pay for its original value. But the
slave is different because that's like land and you give the slave
back. But fundamentally שינוי Shinoy is קונה. Koneh. והכא, V'hacha, in our
case, about shearing it and giving birth, והכא קנסא הוא דקקניס, V'hacha
Knasa Hu Dekakanis,
the fact the reason that you have to give the shearings and
the calf back is just a monetary fine. But fundamentally you should
be קונה. Koneh. אמרי, Omri, no. So that seemed to be a
good proof, but the גמרא Gemara says not necessarily, not so fast.
אמרי רבי מאיר לדיבריהם דרבנן קאמר להו. Omri Rabbi Meir L'divreihem D'rabbanan
Ka'amar Lehu. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir might just be responding to the
Rabbis over there with the slave and the animal that got old
within the Rabbis' own position. לדידי, L'didi, as far as I, רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, am concerned, שינוי אינו קונה, Shinoy Eino Koneh, שינוי
Shinoy is not קונה Koneh at all. ואפילו בהמה נמי, V'afilu Beheima
Nami, and I would say you can even say הרי שלך לפניך
Harei shelcha lefanecha on the בהמה. Beheima. Okay? My position is שינוי
אינו קונה, Shinoy Eino Koneh, you give them both back. אלא לדידכו
דאמריתו שינוי קונה, Ela L'didchu D'amritu Shinoy Koneh, according to you that
you do
hold שינוי Shinoy is קונה, Koneh, אודו לי מיהת בעבדא דכקרקע דמי,
Odu Li Mi'as B'avda D'k'karka Dami, at least you should concede
that the slave you can give back and say הרי שלך לפניך
Harei shelcha lefanecha because slave is like land and it's not acquired
through גזילה Gezeila and therefore you never own it and therefore even
if it gets old you can give it back. So shouldn't you
at least concede the case of a slave? Okay? ואמרי ליה רבנן,
V'amri Lei Rabbanan, and the Rabbis would say back to him, לא,
עבדא כמטלטלי דמי. Lo, Avda K'metalteli Dami. No, we don't agree. We
think slaves are like chattel, which is a whole major debate. Okay,
so even though it's true that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's stated position
there, distinguishing between the slave and the animal, make it clear that
the animal he's saying שינוי Shinoy is קונה, Koneh, the גמרא Gemara
is saying he might not be saying that's his own position, he
might be sort of arguing that within the position of the חכמים.
Chachamim. All right. תא שמע, Ta Shma, let's try again to prove
which way רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds.
לצבוע לו אדום וצבעו שחור, L'tzvo Lo Adom Utzva'o Shachor, you give
wool to a dyer to dye it red and he goes and
makes a mistake and dyes it black. שחור וצבעו אדום, Shachor Utzva'o
Adom, or the reverse. רבי מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו. Rabbi
Meir Omer Nosin Lo D'mei Tzemro. You go ahead and you the
dyer, you keep the wool, you were קונה Koneh the wool with
the שינוי Shinoy because now you made it something different, it's red
or black and different than it was originally and different what the
owner wanted. So you're קונה Koneh it with a שינוי Shinoy and
you pay him for the wool. Okay? So that seems pretty clear.
The גמרא Gemara says, דמי צמרו. D'mei Tzemro. דמי צמרו אין, D'mei
Tzemro In, yes
you pay him for the value of the wool. דמי צמרו ושבחו
לא, D'mei Tzemro V'shvacho Lo, you don't pay him for the wool
and now its improved value with the... It's not only the value,
meaning if שינוי shinui was אינו קונה, eino koneh, you should be
giving back the wool with the dye, maybe if he refuses because
he wanted it a different color, you keep it and you pay
him and you pay him its value. But either way, if it's
fundamentally שינוי אינו קונה, shinui eino koneh, the owner should now also
have own the increase. But that's not what you're paying him. ודמי
צמרו ושיבחו לא ואי סלקא דעתך סבר רבי מאיר שינוי אינו קונה
דמי
צמרו ושיבחו בעי למיתב ליה. v'dmei tzimro u'shivcho lo v'ee salka daitach
savar Rabi Meir shinui eino koneh d'mei tzimro u'shivcho ba'ei lemeitav lei.
You should now have to give him back—so he now owns the
wool which is with the additional value of the red dye. You're
not קונה koneh it. He was קונה koneh it even though you
made a mistake. So you see—so why—so so that's what you should
be saying, he should get the wool, the dyed wool back if
שינוי shinui is not
קונה. koneh. אלא לאו שמע מינה קסבר רבי מאיר שינוי קונה. ela
lav shma mina kasavar Rabi Meir shinui koneh. רבי מאיר Rabi Meir
holds שינוי קונה shinui koneh so you were קונה koneh the wool,
okay, and you—and, you know, and you improved it, you're קונה koneh
the wool and you pay him back the cost of the wool.
והכא קנסא הוא דקקניס שמע מינה. v'hacha knasa hu d'kakanis shma mina.
It's only a fine. The reason you give back the shearings or
the calf is because of a fine because you're a גזלן. gazlan.
And implicitly why would you not pay him for the improvement in
the case of the wool? Because since it's only a fine, then
it's only if you like are a willful גזלן. gazlan. If you're
just a tradesman and you made an honest mistake and you did
black instead of red or even a negligent mistake, that's not a
reason to fine you. So fundamentally you're קונה koneh and you pay
him for the wool whereas in the גזלן gazlan fundamentally you're קונה
koneh but because you're a גזלן gazlan you pay him back the
shearings and the calf. Okay. שמע מינה. shma mina. The גמרא Gemara
says you're right, that is actually a good proof. Okay. איכא דאמרי.
ika d'amri. That's one version of the question we had in רבי
מאיר. Rabi Meir. Does he hold שינוי קונה shinui koneh and קנס
knas or does he hold שינוי אינו קונה? shinui eino koneh? איכא
דאמרי ika d'amri others say הא לאו איבעיא לן. ha lav ibaya
lan. That was never our question. מדאפיך רב ותני. m'dafeich Rav v'tani.
Since רב Rav reversed the ברייתא braita we quoted earlier about the
slaves
and the animal that got old. How did he teach
that ברייתא? braisa? גזל פרה והזקינה עבדים והזקינו משלם כשעת הגזילה דברי
רבי מאיר. gazal parah v'hizkina avadim v'hizkinu m'shaleim kishat hagezeilah divrei Rabi
Meir. רבי מאיר Rabi Meir now is the one that is saying
that you pay both of those כשעת הגזילה. kishat hagezeilah. Okay? You
were קונה koneh them with a שינוי shinui and they got old
and you pay them both as the time that they were stolen.
וחכמים אומרים v'chachamim omrim and it's the חכמים chachamim who distinguish between
the cow and the slave. וחכמים אומרים בעבדים אומר לו הרי שלך
לפניך. v'chachamim omrim b'avadim omer lo harei shelcha l'fanecha. By the slaves
you can say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha l'fanecha. You're not קונה
koneh them because slaves are like קרקע. karka. So if רבי מאיר
Rabi Meir is saying is the first one to speak and he's
the one to say both slaves and בהמה beheimah you get to
keep—because, you know, the only way to explain it is
you keep them and you pay for the original value, the only
way to explain that is because שינוי shinui is קונה. koneh. Okay?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. וחכמים אומרים בעבדים אומר לו
הרי שלך לפניך. v'chachamim omrim b'avadim omer lo harei shelcha l'fanecha. So
in that version, וודאי לרבי מאיר שינוי קונה. vadai l'Rabi Meir shinui
koneh. So certainly the only way to explain for רבי מאיר Rabi
Meir why you are stuck with the old cow and the old
slaves is because of שינוי קונה. shinui koneh. If שינוי shinui wasn't
קונה, koneh, you could say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha l'fanecha and
give them both back. So according to the way that רב Rav
has רבי מאיר Rabi Meir teaching that you're stuck with the old
cow and the old slave, there's no question that רבי מאיר Rabi
Meir holds שינוי קונה. shinui koneh. But yet there's still another version
of a question we had within רבי מאיר'ס Rabi Meir's position of
the קנס. knas. Okay, so רבי מאיר Rabi Meir holds שינוי קונה
shinui koneh והכא קנסא הוא דקקניס ליה v'hacha knasa hu d'kakanis lei
and by the shearings and the calf, the reason you had to
give it back is because of a fine because you're a גזלן.
gazlan. וכי קמבעיא לן v'ki kamba'ya lan and what was our question
about רבי מאיר? Rabi Meir? וכי קמבעיא לן הכי קמבעיא לן. v'ki
kamba'ya lan hachi kamba'ya lan. This was our question. כי קקניס במזיד.
ki kakanis b'meizid. When רבי מאיר Rabi Meir made his fine, did
he make it only in somebody that was a willful גזלן gazlan
that you can't keep the increase that you got because of שינוי
shinui even though you should be קונה koneh and you have to
give it back? אבל בשוגג לא קניס. aval b'shogeg lo kanis. And
in the case where somebody was a non-intentional גזלן, gazlan, you know,
then you would not—we would not make this fine. And you might
be remembering that was the case a minute ago about the dying
of the wool, okay? And that רבי מאיר Rabi Meir did not
make a fine there. He said you keep the wool and you
pay for the wool, you don't give back the increased value. So
that's how we're going to end up. Okay, but that was—so if
you were remembering what we said before, you already know the answer.
But this is the question. We know that רבי מאיר Rabi Meir
giving back the shearings and the calf is a type of a
fine. Is it only for case of a somebody who's a willful
גזלן? gazlan? או דילמא o dilma
or do we say אפילו בשוגג נמי קניס afilu b'shogeg nami kanis
that רבי מאיר Rabi Meir says I don't want to start making
distinctions, were you intentional or not intentional? We're going to make a
fine across the board anytime it wasn't yours, you don't get to
keep the improvement through a שינוי? Shinui? Okay, but it's fundamentally a
fine. So does he apply it to שוגג Shogeg as well? או
דלמא אפילו בשוגג נמי קניס? O dilma afilu b'shogeg nami kanis? תא
שמע, Ta shema, come in here. חמישה גובי מן המכוררין. Chamisha govi
min hamachurarin. There are five types of people that money is owed
to them that they can only collect from unencumbered property, not property
with liens. Meaning, if Reuven owes me a thousand dollars, I can
go knock on Reuven's door and demand that he pays me from
money in his bank account, any stuff he's got in his house,
anything that he owns,
that's unencumbered property. That's what's called
מכוררין, machurarin, so like בני חורין, bnei chorin, free. As opposed to
property with liens. What's a property with a lien? That's real estate.
And not real estate that he owns, but that he has sold.
So after Reuven borrowed a thousand dollars from me, any real estate
that he, I have a lien on all of his real estate.
And if he sells property, then I can go, if I can't
collect my thousand dollars from Reuven directly, I can go to Shimon
who bought Reuven's property after Reuven borrowed the money from me and
after I got my lien on his property. Now Shimon has bought
it and now I can go ahead and I can collect from
that property because of my lien. And the reason for real estate
is because you can't hide away real estate and that allows people
to lend money because they know that they will always have that
property will always be there and if they have liens they'll always
be able to collect. So that's the principle of the difference between
unencumbered,
מכוררין, machurarin, and משועבדים. meshoabadim. Now,
but there are five people who you are not allowed to collect,
there are no liens that they're owed money but they don't have
liens and they can only collect from unencumbered property. Who are they?
Let's take a look.
ואלו הן פירות ושבח פירות. V'elu hen peiros u'shvach peiros. So those
are the two we're going to look at. What's a case of
פירות peiros and
שבח פירות? shvach peiros?
Shimon steals Reuven's property, real estate. He claims it's his. We're calling
him a גזלן gazlan but often there's a whole question of who
really has title. People
maybe are willfully stealing it or they honestly think they have title,
but that's what it's going to turn out to be. That Shimon
has now claiming that this, is trying to steal Reuven's property and
he's claiming it's his. And then he goes ahead and Shimon sells
it to Levi. Levi now and he says to Levi when he
sells him the property, "If anybody takes this property from you claiming
that I didn't have a right to sell it to you, I
will promise to make it up to you, to make it good."
He accepts אחריות, achrayus, he accepts like insurance to reimburse Levi
if that property is ever seized because it did not rightfully belong
to Shimon. And then lo and behold Reuven comes and Reuven proves
in court that that property was his and he takes it from
Levi. Levi now goes back to Shimon and says, "Give me back
the money
that I paid you for that property." So when he's trying to
collect the principal of the money that he paid for the property,
that he can collect from liens
on Shimon's property and if Shimon sold it elsewhere he can collect.
That's a fixed amount. He spent a hundred thousand dollars on the
property, he has a hundred thousand dollar lien and therefore when Levi
bought it from Shimon and therefore he can go collect it from
even if Shimon sells his other real estate.
However, let's say Levi went ahead and what he purchased was an
apple orchard. And he went ahead and he's now been harvesting the
apples for the last ten years.
Okay, and now
when Reuven comes to collect his property back and take his property
back he says, "By the way, not only was that my property,
all of those apples that you've been harvesting and selling, that was
produced by my property. You gotta pay me back for that." So
he demands, that's called פירות. peiros. So he demands all that פירות
peiros back from Levi. Levi now goes to Shimon to make good.
Okay, but that where Levi is now trying to get compensated from
Shimon, Shimon who sold him this stolen property, that's פירות. peiros. In
that case he can only collect from Shimon's unencumbered property. Why? Because
there's no fixed amount. And that's the general principle here. You don't
know how much the פירות peiros are going to be. Are the
פירות peiros going to be a thousand dollars, a million dollars, how
many years of פירות, peiros, how successful is it going to be?
So that's the principle. leans it's not fair to the people that
purchase שמעון's Shimon property to have a lien where you do not
know the how big or small the lien is. So the principal
of the land the hundred thousand dollars that he has liens. If
he has to get compensated for the פירות peiros that he took
from the land okay because it's not able to determine how big
or small that will be he does not have any liens based
on those פירות. peiros. What's שבח פירות? shvach peiros? שבח פירות shvach
peiros is let's say he didn't actually you know
get at the actual apples but he now has made you know
principal improvement in the land itself. He's put in a lot of
manure and he's planted trees and he's done a lot of things.
He's improved the property but he hasn't yet like reaped the benefit
but he's put in a lot of money to improve the property.
And now when you know when ראובן Reuven comes to seize it
back it's now worth a hundred thousand dollars it's worth two hundred
thousand. So you know let's say a hundred fifty thousand for for
illustration purposes. So the first hundred thousand he has liens for ראובן
Reuven for שמעון Shimon and he can collect from שמעון's Shimon encumbered
property. The next fifty thousand though that's שבח פירות shvach peiros and
because again we don't know was the improvement going to be fifty
five zero five hundred thousand? So therefore there are no liens for
the שבח פירות shvach peiros for the improvements he made and when
לוי Levi comes to collect that from שמעון Shimon שמעון Shimon he
could only collect it from שמעון's Shimon unencumbered property. Okay that was
a very big explanation but that's what we're going to focus on.
Okay פירות ושבח פירות peiros v'shvach peiros so those things which don't
have a fixed value they can there's no liens for them.
והמקבל עליו לזונות בן אשתו ובת אשתו v'hamkabel alav l'zonos ben ishto
uvas ishto בן אשתו ובת אשתו ben ishto uvas ishto let's say
somebody marries a woman and maybe he has kids from another wife
or whatever and he says the wife this woman says I will
only agree to marry you if you make take accept upon yourself
a financial obligation that after I die you are going to continue
to make sure you know that my daughter my son are provided
for from the estate. Okay because they don't inherit her the her
money goes to the husband. Okay so he accepts that responsibility. But
because that's a non-fixed amount you know now they're going to get
supported from the estate for one year for twenty years you know
until they get married? Who knows how much? There are no liens
on that. So the son and the daughter have a right to
collect from from the husband okay but only from unencumbered property. Okay
חוב שאין בו אחריות. chov she'ein bo achrayus. Now let's just a
normal debt that you did not write in the document that there
is a lien so you left it out of the document so
then there's no lien. וכתובת אשה שאין בה אחריות v'kesubas isha she'ein
ba achrayus or if you didn't or a כתובה kesuba which is
a type of a debt document that you did not write in
the document itself that there are liens. Anyway those are the things
that you can only collect from unencumbered property. Now how's this relevant
to us? מאן תנא ליה דאמר אחריות לאו טעות סופר הוא? man
tana lei d'amar achrayus lav taus sofer hu? רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
So the fact that it assumes that a document without a lien
written in
it
therefore means that you do not have a lien that's actually debated
in the גמרא. Gemara. There's a position that says אחריות טעות סופר
הוא. achrayus taus sofer hu. The writing of in the document itself
that you have liens if that gets left out that's just a
mistake of the scribes. Anybody who lends money and who bothers to
write a document to prove it and to document it we assume
that there are liens and the person wanted liens on the on
the property. So even if it's not in the שטר shtar it's
not in the writ nevertheless there's always liens. That's the position of
אחריות טעות סופר. achrayus taus sofer. We know this משנה mishnah shows
that you know or a ברייתא beraisa whatever that that we don't
say that. That if there are not liens in the document you
don't have liens. That is the position we know that's the position
of אחריות לאו טעות סופר. achrayus lav taus sofer. The leaving it
off is not a mistake it's intentional and you don't have liens
and we know that that is רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. So
we know that this whole teaching about the things that have to
be from unencumbered is all רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay now where's
this going to get us?
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וקתני פירות ושבח פירות. v'katani peiros v'shvach peiros.
So it teaches us that the case of פירות ושבח פירות peiros
v'shvach peiros the case I gave of ראובן שמעון ולוי Reuven Shimon
v'Levi right that those are cases that you can collect but unencumbered.
So now we're going to spell out the case. היכי דמי? heichi
dami? What's the case? Now you'll be grateful that I illustrated it
before. כגון שגזל שדה מחבירו. kegon she'gazal sadeh me'chavero. שמעון Shimon stole
from ראובן Reuven a field. ומכרה לאחר u'machra l'acher and he now
sold it to לוי. Levi. והשביחה ve'hishpicha and לוי Levi went ahead
and לוי Levi made capital improvements okay? That's going to be שבח
פירות. shvach peiros. והרי היא יוצאת מתחת ידו ve'harei hi yotzei mi'tachas
yado
and then ראובן Reuven proves it's his field ראובן Reuven takes it
back from לוי. Levi. כשהוא גובה keshe'hu goveh now לוי Levi is
going to come because you know because שמעון basically insured it שמעון
said I will I accept אחריות achrayus responsibility if it's taken from
you. So now Levi is going to go to get, to get
his principal 100,000 and his שבח פירות, shevach peiros, his capital improvements
50,000. He's going to get that to be reimbursed from Levi is
going to go to get that to be reimbursed from Shimon. Okay.
כשהוא גובה, kesheh'hu goveh, גובה את הקרן מנכסים משועבדים. goveh es hakeren
minichasim meshubadim. He's going to collect his principal 100,000 from Shimon from
encumbered property. That was a fixed amount at the time of the
sale, and therefore those are classic liens. ואת השבח, v'es hashevach, שבח
מנכסים בני חורין, shevach minichasim b'nei chorin, and the 50,000 capital improvements,
since it was not known how much that would be, that Levi
collects from Shimon from unencumbered property. דאתא בעל ארעא ושקל ארעא ושבחא.
da'asa ba'al ara v'shakal ara v'shvacha. Now,
okay, that's the description, that's what it talks about, that's the scenario
שבח פירות. shevach peiros. But relevant for us is that is that
is that Reuven was able to take back the land with its
capital improvements from Levi. And here's the thing: similar to the case
of shearing a sheep, okay, where, you know, there, the original owner
took the sheep and the shearings back according to Rabbi Meir, that
was the קנס. knas. So here, the original owner, Reuven, takes the
land back and the improvements, okay, doesn't compensate Levi for the improvements,
just takes the land and the improvements without anything being compensated to
Levi. And Levi has to make, try to make it good with
Shimon. So that's an example of Levi here was an honest guy.
He didn't know that it was stolen. He didn't know, you know,
he wasn't intentionally stealing. And nevertheless, for Rabbi Meir, you know, Reuven
has a right to take the improvements. So you see, without any
compensation, so you see that that Rabbi Meir's קנס knas applies even
in a case of שוגג. shogeg. That was pretty complicated to prove
that, but that's the proof. Okay, so let's take a look. Now,
מאי לאו, mai lav, are we not talking about? בעם הארץ b'am
ha'aretz that Levi is ignorant of the law. דלא ידע דקרקע נגזלת
או אינה נגזלת. d'lo yada d'karka nigzeles o einah nigzeles. He didn't
know whether land halachically could be stolen or not. Now, why is
that relevant? Because, well, we'll see, but it basically means he just
assumed maybe he knew that Reuven that that Shimon stole the land,
but he assumed that the הלכה halacha was that the land was
like other stuff, and if he was going to buy it from
Shimon, then he was going to become a full owner of the
land, right? Just like יאוש ושינוי רשות ye'ush v'shinui reshus or something
of that nature. So even we're assuming he knew the land was
stolen, which I don't know why we're assuming that, okay, but nevertheless,
he could be innocent. He could think that by the time he
buys it from Shimon, he totally owns it יאוש ושינוי רשות, ye'ush
v'shinui reshus, let's call it that. He didn't know the principle that
קרקע אינה נגזלת. karka einah nigzeles. So he thought he had total
rights to it, okay? ואפילו הכי, v'afillu hachi, and even though he
was not willfully stealing from from Reuven, קאתי בעל קרקע ושקל ארעא
ושבחא. ka'asi ba'al karka v'shakal ara v'shvacha. Reuven comes and takes his
land back with the improvements and doesn't reimburse Levi. So you see
that even though Levi here was an innocent שוגג shogeg party, Rabbi
Meir's קנס knas of giving back the benefits, you know, of giving
back the improvements, applies even to a case of שוגג. shogeg. ושמע
מינה בשוגג נמי קניס. ushma mina b'shogeg nami kanis.
And you see that even in a case of שוגג, shogeg, Rabbi
Meir's קנס knas applies. הגמרא hag'moro says, אמי לא, ami lo, no,
you don't have to say that that was the scenario. בלוקח תלמיד
חכם וידע. biloke'ach talmid chacham v'yada. We can assume that Levi maybe
knows the law, and Levi should have known that even after that
that קרקע karka is not stolen, and even with יאוש ye'ush or
whatever, that what if he's using this land, that it's still Reuven's
land, that he doesn't have a right to it. It's still Reuven's;
קרקע karka is not stolen. So Levi is not such an innocent
party, okay? And therefore, that's why it's a case of מזיד, mezid,
and that's why you have to give back the benefit. Now, before
we go on, I want to pause and make two points. Number
one is, you know, the other thing that the הגמרא hag'moro is
assuming here is that Levi knew it was stolen, okay? And then
the only question is: Does he know the law of whether he
has rights to keep it or not, he think or, you know,
because of the principle of קרקע נגזלת karka nigzeles or לא נגזלת?
lo nigzeles? So I don't know why the הגמרא hag'moro assumed
clear, because it's גזילה, gezeilah, not גניבה geneivah or something. But okay,
that's what it's assuming.
More significant is the question about: Wait, why is this relevant? The
reason Rabbi you needed Rabbi Meir's קנס knas was because שינוי קונה.
shinui koneh. And fundamentally, the גזלן gazlan was entitled to the shearings
in that case, and then you had to make a קנס knas
that he had to give it back. But here, קרקע אינה נגזלת.
karka einah nigzeles. So it's not a קנס. knas. Of course, you
know, Reuven
Levi is not entitled to the benefits. There's no שינוי. shinui. קרקע
אינה נגזלת. karka einah nigzeles. I mean, שינוי shinui is irrelevant. And
of course, you know, Reuven gets it back. So why are we
talking about a קנס? knas? So ריב"ד Ravad asks this question and
ריב"ד. Ravad. Basically says no, because even if there's no שינוי *shinuy*
and קרקע *karka* is not נגזלת *nigzelas* or whatever, the fact still
is לוי *Levy* made capital improvements into ראובן *Reuven*'s property. And if
I go onto your property and I make capital improvements, let's say
they're ones that you would want, you know even though I had
absolutely no right to do it, you have to pay me a
certain amount for my labor. Okay, that's a הלכה *halacha*, יורד לתוך
שדה חבירו שלא ברשות *yored l'toch s'dei chaveiro shelo birshus*. So and
here ראובן *Reuven* is paying nothing to לוי *Levy* even for his
labor of making the improvements. So the ראב"ד *Raivad* says that's the
proof, right, it's not a case of שינוי *shinuy* not but if
רבי *Rabbi* why is ראובן *Reuven* not at least paying לוי *Levy*
something for לוי *Levy*'s labor in making those improvements? And if he's
not, it must be a קנס *knas*. So you see that רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s קנס *knas* applies even by שוגג *shogeg* and the
גמרא *Gemara* says no, who says לוי *Levy* was so innocent and
that's why the קנס *knas* applies. Okay, and now finally we wrap
this up based on the easier case of what we had before.
תא שמע *Ta shma* come and hear וצבעו לו אדום וצבעו שחור
שחור וצבעו אדום *vitzvao lo adom vitzvao shachor shachor vitzvao adom* רבי
מאיר אומר נותן לו דמי צמרו *Rabbi Meir omer nosin lo dmei
tzmoro*. You go ahead and you pay, you the dyer keep the
wool and you pay him for the wool because שינוי *shinuy* is
קונה *koneh*. דמי צמרו אין *Dmei tzimro in* you pay him for
the wool, דמי צמרו ושבחו לא *dmei tzimro v'shvacho lo* you don't
actually give him the improvement, you don't give him back the wool,
and it's not similar to the case of giving him back the
shearings. So why is it different? In both cases you improve the
guy's property.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says ואי סלקא דעתך בשוגג נמי קנס דמי
צמרו ושבחו בעי למיתב ליה *ve'isalka daatach bishogeg nami knas dmei tzimro
v'shvacho baei l'meisav lo*. And if רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s קנס *knas*
applies even to a case of שוגג *shogeg*, and this is a
great case of שוגג *shogeg*, he didn't want to steal it, he
just accidentally dyed it the wrong thing. So why not give back
the wool with the dye if רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s קנס *knas*
applies in a case of שוגג *shogeg*? אלא לאו שמע מינה במזיד
קנס בשוגג לא קנס *Ela lav shma mina b'meizid knas b'shogeg lo
knas*. You see that רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*'s קנס *knas* applies only
in a case of מזיד *meizid*, not in a case of שוגג
*shogeg*. שמע מינה *Shma mina* and that is a good proof. Okay,
we will end here.